Just a few weeks ago, the federal government proposed a plan for a nearly $800 million
infrastructure project in the state of Illinois.
It's not about maintaining bridges or repaving highways, but it is about building barriers
to defend Lake Michigan from a fish.
It's the Asian carp, a fish that has already wreaked environmental havoc up and down the
Mississippi River watershed.
NewsHour Weekend's Megan Thompson has our report.
Carly Gilpin Jr. fires up his boat and heads out to fish a stretch of the Illinois River,
about 100 miles west of Chicago.
He's spent most of his adult life working on the lakes and rivers of the upper Midwest.
I'm a third generation commercial fisherman.
I've been doing it for about 22, 23 years.
Like a typical fisherman, Gilpin gets an early start.
He drives while an assistant sets out the nets.
You know what you got left?
Not very much.
Okay.
Now let's see if we can scare him.
What comes next?
Not so typical.
Go ahead, Doug.
This is how you catch Asian carp.
The loud sounds startle the fish and push them into the nets.
The other unusual thing?
These fish jump.
The flopping, flailing fish are an invasive species wreaking havoc on lakes and rivers
across the south and midwest.
Gilpin and the other fishermen out here today are employed by the state of Illinois.
Their mission?
Pull as many carp out of the river as they can.
Kevin Irons runs the program.
So whenever any of these carps are out of balance, there's too many of them, they're
going to have catastrophic ecological effects.
That's our silver carp.
There are four types of Asian carp, but bighead and silver cause the most trouble.
They reproduce faster than other fish.
They grow very quickly and can get to over 100 pounds.
And they gobble up plankton and algae, pushing out the native fish.
The carp were first brought to the southern U.S. from Asia in the 1960s to help clean
ponds and fish farms, but some escaped to nearby rivers and lakes.
So places that were once prized fisheries for fish like smallmouth bass or walleye become
primarily Asian carp habitat.
Joel Brammeyer heads the environmental nonprofit, The Alliance for the Great Lakes.
Brammeyer explains that over the last three decades, the carp have moved up the Mississippi
and through its tributaries.
Today the leading edge of the population hovers about 50 miles from Lake Michigan.
The fear now?
The carp could get into Lake Michigan and then into the other four great lakes.
Their most likely path is a series of canals dug in the Chicago area in the 1800s to connect
Lake Michigan to the Mississippi River system.
The canals provided new shipping lanes, carried away sewage and were hailed as a great feat
of engineering.
But it also created a whole set of new problems.
Brammeyer says Asian carp in the Great Lakes could spell disaster for the region's environment
and economy, which is highly dependent on tourism and sport fishing.
We've got fish like lake trout and walleye and yellow perch that form the backbone of
a $7 billion sport fishery.
These fish are the kind that can get pushed out.
And then there's that issue of all that jumping.
And where they've really gotten established, they've basically shut down streams and lakes
from recreation because for one, when you powerboat through Asian carp habitat, silver
carp in particular jump out of the water and can actually hit people in the boats.
Over the last two decades, officials across the upper Midwest have been sounding alarms
and spending hundreds of millions of state and federal dollars to try to keep the carp
out.
Currently the biggest and most expensive defense lies in the Chicago Canal about 25 miles
from Lake Michigan.
We actually have three operating electrical barriers.
Chuck Shea is a project manager for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, which operates a
series of specially designed underwater electrical barriers.
So the electricity is very rapidly turning on and off.
Three sets of eight tons steel bars send electrical pulses into the water above.
As the fish comes into the electrical field, it gets a stronger and stronger electrical
shock and most fish will turn around.
Shea says this is the largest barrier of its kind in the world.
The Army Corps says the biggest danger is the risk of electrical shock to boaters who
might pass through.
They should watch any children or pets that are on board and everybody should stay away
from the edges of the boat.
The three fences and a fourth slated for 2021 cost $270 million to build.
In addition to maintenance of the barriers, staffed around the clock cost around $16 million
a year.
Do you ever just look at this and think, oh my gosh, all of this for some fish?
Well, it's more than just some fish though.
There's an entire ecosystem in the Great Lakes that's of concern and that has great
economic as well as environmental benefits.
Shea says the barrier has been successful in protecting those benefits.
This tagged fish downstream and have never seen any tagged fish get through, but shea
admits the system's not foolproof.
It would be very difficult for any fish to swim directly through the electrical fields
when they're on and operating, but I don't know that we can say anything in life is absolutely
100% effective.
In fact, in 2017, an Asian carp was found beyond the barrier, about nine miles from entering
Lake Michigan.
In 2010, another carp was caught about six miles from Lake Michigan.
Carp DNA has also been detected in the waterways and even in Lake Michigan itself.
There's debate over whether the fish slipped through the barrier or made it into the waters
some other way.
The discoveries further stoked regional tensions over the issue.
The state of Michigan, with its 3,300 miles of Great Lakes coastline, has long pressured
Illinois to do more to stop the carp.
In 2009, Michigan and four other states sued Illinois in a bid to shut down the Chicago
canals to keep the carp out of Lake Michigan.
The lawsuit went nowhere and other talk of taking the drastic step of closing the canals
has met stiff opposition in Illinois because billions of dollars of freight travel through
the area's waterways every year.
In this region, we ship probably 25 to 35 million tons annually.
Then direct tens of thousands of jobs are directly involved with this industry.
Dell Wilkins is the president of Illinois Marine Towing, a major shipping company.
He agrees Asian carp must be stopped, but not at the expense of the massive barges carrying
everything from grain to fuel to cement up and down the rivers.
We look at the Asian carp as a threat as well to the Lake Michigan region.
Let's understand how we move to be able to mitigate that risk and find a way to have
a win-win solution versus a win-lose solution.
Evelyn Sanguennetti, Illinois' outgoing Republican Lieutenant Governor, agrees.
She's helped oversee the state's battle against Asian carp.
In our waterways, there is commerce.
So that is a balance that oftentimes we're encountering.
Since those discoveries of carp beyond the electric barrier, the state of Illinois has
launched a number of projects to keep them out of the Great Lakes.
Their favorite fishing spots can be ruined by aquatic invaders.
Their public awareness campaigns.
Remove, drain, dry.
And regular monitoring of the waterways to keep tabs on where the fish are.
It goes with that other campaign that we have, which goes something like this.
If you can't beat them, then you eat them.
That's right, the state's trying to get people to eat Asian carp, a fish that Americans have
never embraced as food.
A program at the University of Illinois serves up more than 10,000 pounds of carp every year
in its dining halls.
That's really good.
But the state program that pays fishermen like Charlie Gilpin Jr. to catch as many fish
as they can is making the biggest dent.
Kevin Irons of the Department of Natural Resources helped launch it in 2010.
All Asian carp all the time is our little mantra.
The program's price tag of just over $1 million per year is covered by the U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency.
Nine teams of professional fishermen can each catch up to three tons of carp in a day,
sometimes more.
Biologists ride along to document the catch.
Charlie Gilpin Jr. used to catch and sell buffalo fish in western Illinois where he's
from, but then the Asian carp arrived about 15 years ago.
In those areas, you can't target the native fish that you used to because of the abundance
of the Asian carp.
So you kind of had to join in and just catch the Asian carp.
Gilpin says before this program, he was struggling to make a living fishing, let alone on Asian
carp, which hasn't caught on widely as food.
So this program has helped him out a lot.
And his father, who's out here fishing too.
At the end of each day, the fishermen tow their catch to a nearby town.
The carp are transferred to huge bins and stored in a refrigerated truck.
Anyone can come get them free of charge.
They just can't be eaten by people since they win a few hours without being refrigerated.
So they're made into things like fish fertilizer and bait.
The day we were there, a pet food maker showed up to gladly take the free ingredients.
If we load up, I got cooler device, we're going to ice it down, tarp it, and I'm going
to take it home and get it processed.
Since this program started in 2010, the state says it has caught 7.5 million pounds of carp,
decreasing the leading edge population by 93%.
Do you hope someday that you can just stop fishing for Asian carp in this part of the river?
It'd be great, right?
I'm concerned with people thinking eradication is the ultimate goal.
It's really, really hard to do.
And that's why there's a whole new line of carp defenses being planned at the Brandon
Road Lock and Dam, about 10 miles before the existing electric barriers.
The Army Corps is proposing to install more electric barriers, underwater sound machines
to scare the fish, and something called an air bubble curtain to flush out any carp caught
between barges traveling through.
The state of Illinois has agreed to sponsor the project reluctantly, worried about the
costs.
It's very easy to automatically come to the conclusion that the sky is falling.
And so this is why it's so important that we not have a knee-jerk reaction to this.
You can stop Asian carp from devastating the Great Lakes.
Meanwhile, the state of Michigan is gung-ho, even launching a campaign to pressure Illinois
to take a stronger stand.
All the states need to come together and not make money the issue.
The issue is these carp.
But the money is an issue.
A new price tag for the project was announced in November.
Nearly $778 million, three times the original estimate.
Congress must now approve the plan and provide some funding.
Previous talks between Illinois and Michigan about sharing the remaining costs are now
up in the air, given the new price tag and the fact that new governors are taking over
both states this month.
While the politicians sort it all out, the fishermen in Illinois continue their work
hauling ton after ton of big head and silver carp.
Charlie Gilpin Jr. says he's proud to be a part of the mission and even sees a silver
lining for what he calls his dying profession.
With the abundance of the fish, it's kind of giving us another outlet.
It's kind of a blessing and a curse.
It may be our savior.
Thank you.